<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE codeBook
SYSTEM "http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/files/DDI/Version2-1.dtd">
    <codeBook>
        <docDscr>
            <citation>
                <titlStmt>
                    <titl>National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS), 2015</titl>
                    <IDNo>50014</IDNo>
                </titlStmt>
                <prodStmt>
                    <producer abbr="ICPSR">
                        <ExtLink URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/images/icpsr-logo.gif" title="ICPSR Logo" role="image"/>
                        Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research
                        <ExtLink URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/" title="URL of ICPSR Web Site" />
                    </producer>
                </prodStmt>
                <verStmt>
                    <version date="2017-03-28"></version>
                </verStmt>
                <holdings URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/xmldocs/STUDY/34968.xml"></holdings>
            </citation>
        </docDscr>
        <stdyDscr>
            <citation>
                <titlStmt>
                    <titl>National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS), 2015</titl>
                    <altTitl>N-SSATS, 2015</altTitl>
                    <IDNo agency="ICPSR">50014</IDNo>
                </titlStmt>
                <rspStmt>
                    <AuthEnty affiliation="United States Department of Health and Human Services. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality">United States Department of Health and Human Services. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality</AuthEnty>
                </rspStmt>
                <prodStmt>
                    <copyright>
                        Some instruments administered as part of this
                        study may contain contents from copyrighted
                        instruments. Reproductions of the instruments
                        are provided solely as documentation for
                        the analysis of the data associated with this
                        collection. Please contact the data producers for
                        information on permissions to use the instruments
                        for other purposes.
                    </copyright>
                    <prodDate>Please see full citation.</prodDate>
                    <fundAg>United States Department of Health and Human Services. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality</fundAg>
                </prodStmt>
                <distStmt>
                    <distrbtr abbr="ICPSR" affiliation="Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan" URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu">
                        <ExtLink URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/images/icpsr-logo.gif" title="Logo" />
                        Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research
                        <ExtLink URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/" title="URL" />
                    </distrbtr>
                    <distDate date="2016-05-10">2016-05-10</distDate>
                </distStmt>
                <serStmt>
                    <serName ID="Series58">National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS) Series</serName>
                </serStmt>
                <verStmt>
                    <version date="2016-02-22">2016-02-22</version>
                </verStmt>
                <verStmt>
                    <version date=" "> </version>
                    <notes> </notes>
                </verStmt>
                <biblCit>United States Department of Health and Human Services. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality. National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS), 2015. ICPSR34968-v2. Ann Arbor, MI: Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research [distributor], 2015-04-25. http://doi.org/10.3886/ICPSR34968.v2</biblCit>
            </citation>
            <stdyInfo>
                    <subject>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">alcohol abuse</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">drug abuse</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">drug treatment</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">health care services</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">HIV</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">intervention</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">substance abuse</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">substance abuse treatment</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">treatment facilities</keyword>
                        <keyword vocab="thesaurus">treatment programs</keyword>
                        <topcClas source="archive" vocab="AHRQMCC subject classifications">AHRQMCC I. Multiple Chronic Conditions</topcClas>
                        <topcClas source="archive" vocab="FENWAY subject classifications">FENWAY VI. Studies That Include Heterosexual Populations</topcClas>
                        <topcClas source="archive" vocab="ICPSR subject classifications">ICPSR IX. Health Care and Health Facilities</topcClas>
                        <topcClas source="archive" vocab="NAHDAP subject classifications">NAHDAP I. National Addiction and HIV Data Archive Program</topcClas>
                        <topcClas source="archive" vocab="SAMHDA subject classifications">SAMHDA XIII. National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS)</topcClas>
                    </subject>
                    <abstract><![CDATA[<p>The 2015 National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS) was conducted between March and November 2015, with a reference date of March 31, 2015. It is the 38th in a series of national surveys begun in the 1970s. The surveys were designed to collect data on the location, characteristics, and use of alcohol and drug abuse treatment facilities and services throughout the 50 states, the District of Columbia, and other U.S. jurisdictions. The Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality, Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA), U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, plans and directs N-SSATS. This report presents tabular information and highlights from the 2015 N-SSATS. It is important to note that percentages in charts, narrative lists, and percentage distributions in tables may not add to 100 percent due to rounding.</p>
					<p>N-SSATS is designed to collect information from all facilities in the United States, both public and private, that provide substance abuse treatment. N-SSATS provides the mechanism for quantifying the dynamic character and composition of the U.S. substance abuse treatment delivery system. N-SSATS collects multipurpose data that can be used to:
					<ul>
					<li>Assist SAMHSA and state and local governments in assessing the nature and extent of services provided in state-supported and other substance abuse treatment facilities and in forecasting substance abuse treatment resource requirements;</li>
					<li>Update SAMHSA’s Inventory of Behavioral Health Services (I-BHS) which includes all known drug and alcohol abuse treatment facilities, both public and private;</li>
					<li>Analyze substance abuse treatment services trends and conduct comparative analyses for the nation, regions, and states;</li>
					<li>Generate the National Directory of Drug and Alcohol Abuse Treatment Programs, a compendium of facilities approved by state substance abuse agencies for the provision of substance abuse treatment;</li>
						<li>Update the information in SAMHSA’s Behavioral Health Treatment Facility Locator, a searchable database of facilities approved by state substance abuse agencies for the provision of substance abuse treatment. 
</li>
					</ul>
					<p>The Treatment Facility Locator is available on the Internet at:
<ExtLink URI="http://findtreatment.samhsa.gov" /></p>]]></abstract>
                    <sumDscr>
                        <timePrd event="single" date="2015" cycle="P1"> </timePrd>
                        <collDate event="start" date="2015-03-31" cycle="P1"> </collDate>
                        <collDate event="end"   date="2015-12-07" cycle="P1"> </collDate>
                        <nation>Please see geographic coverage.</nation>
                        <geogCover>United States</geogCover>
                        <anlyUnit>facility</anlyUnit>
                        <dataKind>survey data</dataKind>
                    </sumDscr>
            </stdyInfo>
            <method>
                <dataColl>
                    <sampProc>There were 17,669 facilities in the survey universe. Of these facilities, 12 percent were found to be ineligible for the survey because they had closed or did not provide substance abuse treatment or detoxification. Of the remaining 15,537 facilities, 14,234 facilities (92 percent) completed the survey and 13,873 (89 percent) were eligible for this report.
					</sampProc>
                    <collMode>computer-assisted telephone interview (CATI)</collMode>
                    <collMode>mail questionnaire</collMode>
                    <collMode>telephone interview</collMode>
                    <collMode>web-based survey</collMode>
                    <cleanOps>Performed consistency checks.</cleanOps>
                    <cleanOps>Created variable labels and/or value labels.</cleanOps>
                    <cleanOps>Standardized missing values.</cleanOps>
                    <cleanOps>Created online analysis version with question text.</cleanOps>
                    <cleanOps>Performed recodes and/or calculated derived variables.</cleanOps>
                    <cleanOps>Checked for undocumented or out-of-range codes.</cleanOps>
                </dataColl>
                <notes><![CDATA[Three data collection modes were employed: a secure web-based questionnaire, a paper questionnaire sent by mail, and a telephone interview. Five weeks before the survey reference date of March 31, 2015, letters were mailed to all facilities to announce the survey. The letters also served to update records with new address information received from the U.S. Postal Service. During the last week of March 2015, a data collection packet (including the SAMHSA cover letter, state-specific letter of endorsement, state profile, information on completing the survey on the web, and a sheet of Frequently Asked Questions) was mailed to each facility. To ease the burden on respondents, many of the data items that typically do not change from year to year were prefilled in the web-based questionnaire for those facilities that had completed the 2014 survey. Respondents could also request a paper questionnaire be sent to them. During the data collection phase, contract personnel were available to answer facilities’ questions concerning the survey. Web-based support for facilities completing the questionnaire on the web was also available. Three weeks after the initial data collection packet mailing, thank you/reminder letters were sent to all facilities. Approximately 8 weeks after the initial packet mailing, non-responding facilities were mailed a second packet. There was no questionnaire in the 2015 second packet. About 2 weeks after the second packet mailing, non-respondents received a reminder telephone call. A third packet containing a hard-copy questionnaire was mailed about 8 weeks after the second packet mailing. Those facilities that had not responded
within 3 to 4 weeks of the reminder call were telephoned and asked to complete the survey by computer-assisted telephone interview (CATI).
]]></notes>
                <anlyInfo>
                    <respRate>There were 17,669 facilities in the survey universe. Of these facilities, 12 percent were found to be ineligible for the survey because they had closed or did not provide substance abuse treatment or detoxification. Of the remaining 15,537 facilities, 14,234 facilities (92 percent) completed the survey and 13,873 (89 percent) were eligible for this report.</respRate>
                </anlyInfo>
            </method>
            <dataAccs>
                <setAvail media="online">
                    <accsPlac URI="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu">Ann Arbor, Mi.:  Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</accsPlac>
                    <notes>Stata system file(s), rda Data file(s), sav Data file(s), stc Data file(s), tsv Data file(s), Data file(s), and electronic documentation.</notes>
                </setAvail>
                <useStmt>
                    <specPerm>Additional special permissions, where applicable, are described in the restrictions field.</specPerm>
                    <restrctn>Users are reminded by the United States Department of
Health and Human Services that these data are to be used solely for statistical analysis and reporting of aggregated information and not for the investigation of specific individuals or treatment facilities.</restrctn>

		<conditions>
		    <![CDATA[
		    <p>Please read the Terms of Use below. If you agree to them, click on the "I Agree" button to proceed. If you do not agree, you can click on the "I Do Not Agree" button to exit this page.</p><p>These data are distributed under the following terms of use. By continuing past this point to the data retrieval process, you signify your agreement to comply with the requirements as stated below:</p><h2>Privacy of RESEARCH SUBJECTS</h2><p>Any intentional identification of a RESEARCH SUBJECT (whether an individual or an organization) or unauthorized disclosure of his or her confidential information violates the PROMISE OF CONFIDENTIALITY given to the providers of the information. Disclosure of confidential information may also be punishable under federal law. Therefore, users of data agree:</p><ul><li><p>To use these datasets solely for research or statistical purposes and not for re-identification of specific RESEARCH SUBJECTS.</p></li><li><p>To make no use of the identity of any RESEARCH SUBJECT discovered inadvertently and to report any such discovery to CBHSQ and SAMHDA ( <a href="mailto:samhda-support@icpsr.umich.edu">samhda-support@icpsr.umich.edu</a>)</p></li></ul><h2>Citing Data</h2><p>You agree to reference the recommended bibliographic citation in any of your publications that use SAMHSA data. Authors of publications that use SAMHSA data are required to send citations of their published works to ICPSR for inclusion in a database of related publications (<a href="mailto:bibliography@icpsr.umich.edu">bibliography@icpsr.umich.edu</a>).</p><h2>Disclaimer</h2><p>You acknowledge that SAMHSA and ICPSR will bear no responsibility for your use of the data or for your interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</p><h2>Violations</h2><p>If SAMHSA or ICPSR determines that this terms of use agreement has been violated, then possible sanctions could include:</p><ul><li><p>Report of the violation to the Research Integrity Officer, Institutional Review Board, or Human Subjects Review Committee of the user's institution. A range of sanctions are available to institutions including revocation of tenure and termination.</p></li><li><p>If the confidentiality of human subjects has been violated, then report of the violation may be made to the Federal Office for Human Research Protections. This may result in an investigation of the user's institution, which can result in institution-wide sanctions including the suspension of all research grants.</p></li> <li><p>Report of the violation of federal law to the United States Attorney General for possible prosecution.</p></li><li><p>Court awarded payments of damages to any individual(s)/organization(s) harmed by the breach of confidential data.</p></li></ul> <h2>Definitions</h2><dl><dt>CBHSQ</dt><dd>Center for Behavioral Health Statistics and Quality</dd><dt>ICPSR</dt><dd>Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research</dd><dt>Promise of confidentiality</dt><dd>A promise to a respondent or research participant that the information the respondent provides will not be disseminated in identifiable form without the permission of the respondent; that the fact that the respondent participated in the study will not be disclosed; and that disseminated information will include no linkages to the identity of the respondent. Such a promise encompasses traditional notions of both confidentiality and anonymity. In most cases, federal law protects the confidentiality of the respondent's identity as referenced in the Promise of Confidentiality. Under this condition, names and other identifying information regarding respondents would be confidential.</dd><dt>Research subject</dt><dd>A person or organization that participates in a research study. A research subject may also be called a respondent. A respondent is generally a survey respondent or informant, experimental or observational subject, focus group participant, or any other person providing information to a study.</dd> <dt>SAMHDA</dt><dd>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Data Archive</dd><dt>SAMHSA</dt><dd>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration</dd></dl>
		    ]]>
		    <p>AVAILABLE.  This study is freely available to the general public.</p>
		</conditions>

		<disclaimer>The original collector of the data, ICPSR,
		and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility
		for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences
		based upon such uses.  </disclaimer>
                    </useStmt>
            </dataAccs>
            <othrStdyMat>
                <othRefs>
                    <citation>
                        <titlStmt>
                            <titl>National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS), 2015</titl>
                        </titlStmt>
                        <holdings>SDA Component</holdings>
                    </citation>
                </othRefs>
            </othrStdyMat>
        </stdyDscr>
        <fileDscr ID="F1">
            <fileTxt ID="Part1">
                <fileName>National Survey of Substance Abuse Treatment Services (N-SSATS), 2015</fileName>
                <fileType>DELIMITED DOC RDATA SAS SPSS STATA</fileType>
            </fileTxt>
            <notes>41554</notes>
        </fileDscr>
    </codeBook>

